Today we're going to talk about five of
the most popular ways to mix cocktails.
Shaking, double shaking, stirring,
building, and blending. In this episode,
I'm going to try and help you understand
which technique you use when you're
making certain drinks, the impact it has
on the drink, and also give you some
examples of drinks that use each
technique. So let's have a look at it.
So before we get into those five
different methods of mixing drinks, we're
going to talk about why exactly you would
do this. And there are three primary
reasons. Number one is to mix the
ingredients together, #2 is to chill the
drink, and #3 is to bring some dilution
to the drink. Whichever method you go
for, you need to be quite intentional
with because it's going to have a big
impact on the texture of the drink
primarily. So first of all, we're going
to talk about shaking.
So when it comes to shaking a cocktail,
there are a few things you really need to
think about. First of all, you want to
make sure you use plenty of ice. Even
though it seems kind of contradictory,
using more ice actually gives you a
slower dilution because the drink stays
nice and cold. Whereas if you just add
one or two ice cubes, they're going to
melt pretty quickly and they're actually
going to dilute the drink before you
reach the texture you're looking for.
Again, whichever shaker you go for, make
sure you seal the two together nice and
tight, and you want to hold onto it with
two hands, one hand on top, one hand
underneath, and when you shake. There are
many different ways to shake a cocktail,
and the evidence seems to suggest that
whichever way you go for can be greatly
effective, as long as you shake it for
around about 12 to 15 seconds. So if you
want to read more about this, you can
read Liquid Intelligence, which does a
lot of work into this, but fundamentally
plenty of headroom. Shake it really hard
end to end and make sure the ice has
plenty of room to travel and the drink
also goes up and down through the shaker.
You don't want to go side to side because
it's just kind of going all over the
place without really mixing. You want to
use the full capacity of the shaker to
get as much back and forth as you
possibly can in the drink. The same
applies for your kind of three piece
shaker. Top and bottom. Make sure you
hold on nice and tight so you don't have
any spillages. Shake, shake, shake. Could
be a kind of up and down, could be a over
the shoulder, could be straight back and
forward. But it has to feel comfortable,
has to get the job done and shake nice
and hard. Really important. However you
shake, shake hard. But when would you do
this?So. These are kind of rules of
thumb. They're made to be broken, but
they're also there for a particular
reason. So shaking a cocktail is usually
done when there's citrus in the drink,
when there's dairy in the drink, or when
you want to really aerate the drink to
get it nice and vibrant and bubbly and
foamy and alive. So this is found in lots
of different cocktails. Daiquiri, Last
Word, Paper Plain. These are all shaken
cocktails because they all contain
citrus. But if you want to take this one
step further and get even more texture on
your drink, you can do what's called a
double shake.
So one of the key variations of shake in
a cocktail is called a double shake, and
this incorporates a dry shake. So rather
than just shaking the drink once with
ice, you're actually going to do 2
shakes, once with ice and once without
either dry first or dry second. If you do
the dry shake first, where you just shake
the cocktail to kind of emulsify it, that
would be a dry shake. Whereas if you do
it after the main shake with ice, that's
a reverse dry shake. So both of these
work really well. Experiment with both.
But when I talked about emulsification,
that's kind of important here because
it's going to be used when you
incorporate things like egg white or
aquafaba or even pineapple juice. You can
use this technique in drinks which is
sour based, like a whiskey sour or a
Pisco sour or even something like a white
lady. I actually try and avoid this
process as much as possible because it is
a little bit fiddly. If you're using
things like pineapple juice, egg white
and aquafaba, you do want that really
foamy texture. But if you also use ice
that's fresh out of the freezer, you can
just give it a single really hard shake
over ice and. Avoid the need to do this.
But if your ice has been out of the
freezer a little bit longer, you might
want to do this so you don't shake it too
hard and overly dilute the drink. So now
we've got a shake, we've got a double
shake. We can talk about stirring
cocktails.
So if you're making a drink that doesn't
contain citrus or it's almost entirely
booze, you might want to stir the drink.
And this doesn't add anywhere near as
much aeration as you're shaking and
double shaking. It's kind of silkier,
more refined, a little bit smoother, but
equally powerful. So you do this when
you're making drinks like a. Martini, as
long as it's not a shaken martini, a
Manhattan, a Martinez and an old
fashioned. And if you think about the
texture of those drinks, they're very
elegant, very silky, not kind of
vibrant and alive, which is what you're
going to get with a shaken drink. So
again, the technique for this can be
really simple. You just want to stir the
drink down over lots of ice, using a bar
spoon ideally, but also a chopstick might
work. And then once you reach the level
of dilution you're looking for, strain it
out and you'll get that really nice silky
cocktail. This retains a lot of really
nice aromatics of the drink, but also it
gives a really nice kind of clear final
drink, which obviously if you're shaking
the drink, you're going to aerate it and
lose that. So now we've got our shaken
drinks, our double shaken drinks and our
stirred drinks. We're going to look at
building drinks.
So when it comes to building drinks, what
this means is building the drink in the
glass. Something like a mojito would be a
really good example of this or any drink
that you're going to top with something
like soda water. Tonic or even sparkling
wine. And the reason to do this is to
avoid overly diluting the drink or to
keep the entire pieces of fruit, herbs or
spices in the final drink. So when it
comes to the mojito, you're actually
muddling the mint into the drink and
leaving it in there. But you do have to
be careful that if you're building in the
drink, you don't break the glass when you
muddle too hard. So now we're going to
talk about the final technique today,
which is going to be blending.
So a final technique we can look at,
which is featured in things like a pina
colada and all sorts of frozen cocktails,
is going to be blending drinks. And this
is really useful if you want to leave the
entire fruit in the drink or to get that
kind of really nice blended, smooth,
almost creamy texture. If you can add
something like coconut milk or cream. And
it's just a really interesting way to do
things where you actually blend the ice
completely into the drink rather than
straining it out. So when it comes to
adding ice, if you add a little bit of
ice, you'll get a kind of almost
milkshake texture, whereas if you add a
lot of ice, it'll become very thick,
almost like a slushy. So there's no right
and wrong here. I prefer it a little bit
on the looser side so you can at least.
Drink it rather than eating it, but your
mileage may vary. If you like disco
drinks, you might like them to be kind of
slushy drinks, which is totally fine.
Barlic to get a little bit lighter, a
little bit more pourable, a little bit
more sippable, and we'll see a pina
colada in the future, which I'm very
excited to share with you. So now I've
got really good foundation to build upon.
We've covered some essential bottles,
some essential tools, the importance of
balance, sweetening drinks, seasoning
drinks, all sorts of ways of presenting
the drinks, including ice, clear ice,
garnishes. I think we're pretty much
ready to start mixing some cocktails.